A Guide to the Daniel Bedinger Lucas Papers, 1812-1924, n.d.
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Daniel Bedinger Lucas Papers, 1812-1924, n.d.
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Lucas, Daniel Bedinger, 1836-1909; Lucas, Virginia, b.1838
Ms1995-012
1.8 Cubic Feet 4 boxes
One of the scrapbooks in this collection has been digitized and is available online.
The Daniel Bedinger Lucas papers consist of scrapbooks, correspondence, poems and essays, newspapers, and other materials collected and created by Lucas, including several items created by his sister, Virginia Lucas, also a poet.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The Daniel Bedinger Lucas Papers were donated to Special Collections in May 1995. Additional materials were donated in September 1995. An addtional letter was purchased in 2014.
Alternate Form Available
One of the scrapbooks in this collection has been digitized and is available online.
Biographical Information
Daniel Bedinger Lucas, lawyer and poet, was born March 16, 1836, at "Rion Hall" in Charleston, Virginia (now West Virginia). He attended the University of Virginia, and then studied law under Judge John W. Brockenbrough of Lexington, Virginia. In 1859 he began practicing law at Charleston but moved the next year to Richmond. At the beginning of the Civil War in 1861 he joined the staff of General Henry A. Wise and took part in the Kanawha Valley campaign, but his physical disability from a childhood spine injury kept him from active service in the last years of the war. Toward the end of the war he ran the blockade to defend his friend John Yates Beall, accused of being a Confederate spy, but was unable to defend him against the charges. Beall was executed on Governors Island, New York.
In 1869, Lucas married Lena Tucker Brooke, of Richmond. Their only child, Virginia, was born in 1873. Barred from the practice of law until 1871, due to restrictions on the service of ex-Confederates, Lucas turned to literature and became co-editor of the Baltimore Southern Metropolis. Many of his poems were published in this magazine. He reentered the practice of law in 1871 and took a prominent role in the Democratic party politics of West Virginia, acting as Democratic elector in the elections of 1872 and 1876, to the legislature in 1884 and 1886, and as a member of the supreme court of appeals from 1889 to 1893.
Lucas's volumes of poetry include The Wreath of Eglantine (1869), with poems of his sister, Virginia, and Ballads and Madrigals (1884). He wrote three plays about the Civil War. His books include The Memoir of John Yates Beall (1865) and Nicaragua, War of the Filibusters (1896). He was known as the "poet of the Shenandoah Valley." He died at Rion Hall on June 24, 1909.
Scope and Content
The Daniel Bedinger Lucas papers consist of scrapbooks, correspondence, poems and essays, newspapers, and other materials collected and created by Lucas, including several items created by his sister, Virginia Lucas, also a poet. Topics include Lucas's defense of John Yates Beall, the exploits of adventurer William Walker, the origin of General Robert E. Lee's horse Traveler; and West Virginia politics. There are examples of Lucas's poetry scattered throughout the papers. The 1860 scrapbook includes several interesting pressed flower designs.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged chronologically. Undated materials are at located in boxes 3 and 4.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Local/Regional History and Appalachian South; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Civil War
Contents List
- Issue of the National Intelligencer of Washington City (Washington, D.C.), March 4, 1812. (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Manuscript copy (made in 1880) of "The Cossack Celebration at Shephardstown, Jefferson County, Virginia" (now West Virginia), July 28, 1814. (Box 1, Folder 2)
- "A Study of the Literature of West Virginia" written by Mary Meek Atkeson, Ph.D. 1822-1922. (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Article, "A Blister Plaster, for the Cure of Cacoethes Scribendi" by John S. Gallaher, April 1, 1828. (Box 1, Folder 4)
- One page of The Register, of Shephardstown, West Virginia. Article written by Dr. Harry T. McDonald about the Armory and Arsenal at Harper's Ferry, March 1, 1828. (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Issue of The Hagerstown Mail of Hagerstown, Maryland. May 1, 1829. (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Appendix to the Congressional Globe, February 1844, pp. 337-352, 1844. (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Two letters to William Lucas in Charleston, Virginia, (now West Virginia), 1844. (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Issue of Spirit of Jefferson, newspaper of Charleston, Virginia (now West Virginia), July 23, 1850. (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Article from Charleston, Virginia (now West Virginia) newspaper, written by Lucas,k March 4, 1856. (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Poem written to Lucas, author is an unidentified sibling of Lucas (probably his sister Virginia), January 10, 1859. (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Scrapbook of poetry, newspaper clippings, and pressed flowers (likely by sister, Virginia), 1860? (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Manuscript copy of an article from the New York Herald about the September 1860 court martial and execution of William Walker, whose military and political expeditions in Central America gained him the reputation as the "greatest American filibuster," October 4, 1860. (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Letter from Daniel B. Lucas, writing from the Quarter Master General's Office in Richmond, Virginia, to his brother, April 30, 1861. (Box 1, Folder 14)
- One page from the Daily Enquirer of Richmond, Virginia, 1862. (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Photographs of General Turner Ashby and Daniel Lucas, 1862, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Issue of American and Commercial Advertising of Baltimore, Maryland, December 1, 1863. (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Letter to "John" (John Yates Beall) 1864 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  Scope and Contents
  Letter to John [Yates Beall], dated July 30, 1864 from Richmond. Lucas talks about recent personal and military events. Lucas defended Beall when was tried as a Confederate guerrilla and spy, but Beall was executed on February 4, 1865.
- Letter from Daniel B. Lucas in Canada, to his cousin Virginia. Mentions death of John Yates Beall, March 12, 1865. (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Receipt from Gibb Company, Merchants Tailors, in Montreal to Lucas, August 22, 1865. (Box 1, Folder 19)
- One page from the Winchester Times, with an article about the dedication of the Stonewall Cemetery, October 31, 1866. (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Two issues of the National Intelligencer, August 1 and August 22, 1867. (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Letters from R. N. Engle at Elston Bank to Lucas about the tract of land he received, May 13 and May 21, 1869. (Box 1, Folder 22)
- A statement of Daniel Lucas' account after the addition of Edward Lucas' estate, 1868. (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Scrapbook of newspaper clippings. Topics include the death of John Yates Beall, politics, the Civil War, and speaking engagements of Daniel Lucas, 1869-1876. (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Issue of The Saturday Review of Politics, Literature, Science, and Art, April 10, 1869. (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Check written by Lucas to Charles J. Faulkner for $200.00, August 17, 1869. (Box 1, Folder 26)
- One page from the Winchester Times, in which Lucas wrote an article, 1869. (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Issue of Virginia Free Press-The Old Family Journal, 1871. (Box 1, Folder 28)
- January issue of the Westminister Review, 1872 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Letter and statement of account from P. H. Kennedy to Daniel Lucas about Edward Lucas' estate, January 22, 1872. (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Essay (or speech) in praise of the Democratic Party, 1876(?). (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Scrapbook with newspaper clippings about William Lucas, Daniel Lucas, politics, and the Civil War, 1876-1893. (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Robert Lucas' Survivor's Pension from the U.S. Department of Interior for serving in the Virginia Militia, 1878. (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Issue of The Morgan Mercury, from Berkley Springs, West Virginia, December 7, 1878. (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Issue of the Weekly New Mexican, July 19, 1880. (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Letter from A.W. Kerchival to Daniel Lucas, January 25, 1882. (Box 1, Folder 36)
- "Ballads and Madrigals," a book of poems written by Daniel Lucas, 1884. (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Scrapbook of newspaper clippings of poetry, songs, witticisms, essays, etc., compiled by Virginia Lucas, 1888(?). (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Issue of Spirit of Jefferson, a Charleston, West Virginia, newspaper, June 12, 1888. (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Ribbon from a Memorial Day celebration and Confederate reunion in Norfolk, Virginia, 1889. (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Letter from Okey Johnson to Lucas, December 24, 1889. (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Letter from Marcus Wright, War of Records Office, War Department of Washington, to Lucas, April 7, 1893. (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Notebook of household accounts and poetry in manuscript by Lena Lucas from Rion Hall, October 31, 1894. (Box 1, Folder 43)
- "Walker in Nicaragua," a typescript essay by Daniel B. Lucas, 1895. (Box 1, Folder 44)
- Letters between Joseph M. Broun and J. Johnston about how General Robert E. Lee obtained his horse Traveler, 1895-1899. (Box 1, Folder 45)
- Issue of The Winchester Times, February 17, 1897. (Box 1, Folder 46)
- "The Last Confederate Pay-roll" by Joseph M. Broun of Charleston, Kanawha County, West Virginia. Manuscript essay, 1897. (Box 1, Folder 47)
- "The Last Confederate Pay-roll" by Joseph M. Broun. Typescript copy of essay, [1897]. (Box 1, Folder 48)
- Letter from Marcus J. Wright to Lucas, July 22, 1898. (Box 1, Folder 49)
- Program of the Eleventh Annual Reunion of the Charlestown Society, song written by Lucas, January 6, 1900. (Box 1, Folder 50)
- "Dramatic Works of Daniel Bedinger Lucas," a book of plays by Lucas, 1913. (Box 1, Folder 51)
- "The Land Where We Were Dreaming," a book of poems by Daniel Lucas, 1913. (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Issue of The Washington Post, July 13, 1921. (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Pages from a scrapbook with topics about forestry and trees; includes miscellaneous poetry. Compiled by Virginia Lucas, 1923-1930. (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Life of John Brown, by Michael Gold, 1924 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Newspaper account of the 1865 death of John Wilkes Booth. (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Drawing of the Pennsylvania, Virginia, and North Carolina colonies (1745-56) with a line showing Washington's journey in 1751. (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Notebook of manuscript poems written by Daniel B. Lucas, with an index to the poems. (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Argument as to why Jefferson County, West Virginia, should have been considered part of the Union under the act of July 4th, 1864. Author unknown, though probably Daniel B. Lucas. (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Account in an unidentified newspaper about the "Last Days of the War" (Confederate view). (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Miscellaneous papers. (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Miscellaneous correspondence. (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Miscellaneous poetry. (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Notebook of miscellaneous poetry. (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Miscellaneous papers about John Yates Beall. (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Framed photograph of Daniel Lucas. (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Notebook of manuscript notes, presumably written by Lucas. (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Newspaper article about General Robert E. Lee's description of Traveller, his horse, newspaper unknown. (Box 4, Folder 2)
- "List of Relics Contributed to the World's Fair Exposition" by Daniel Lucas. (Box 4, Folder 3)
- A notebook of poems written in manuscript by an unidentified person. (Box 4, Folder 4)